A Guide to the Papers of Milton L. Grigg 1924-1982 and n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Milton L. Grigg 1924-1982 and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6478-c
This collection consists of ca. 1,850 items (6 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library by Mrs. Milton Grigg of Charlottesville, Virginia, on December, 1986.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 1,850 items (6 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet), ca. 1924-1982, and undated, and contains photographs, drawings, blueprints, and additional papers of the Charlottesville architect, Milton Grigg (1905-1982), and includes examples of church architecture, the restoration of historic buildings, and contemporary dwellings. Grigg attended the University of Virginia Architecture School during 1924-1929.
Photographs form the bulk of this collection and comprise the first series; they are divided into two subseries of identified and unidentified photographs. The identified structures are arranged according to the city or county in which they are found and are listed individually in the box listing. The unidentified photographs were simply grouped together as either churches or houses.
The remainder of the collection was placed in a second series of miscellaneous files consisting of a list of architectural projects by Grigg; biographical information concerning Grigg; papers regarding a church architectural tour of Europe; church projects undertaken by Grigg which are listed alphabetically by the name of the church in the box listing; slide show presentation notes concerning church architecture and a reel-to-reel tape describing the slides; description of a business trip to Canberra, Austrailia; blueprints of Belle Haven, Edgemont, and a Manager's House for an estate at Carters Bridge; and correspondence. The correspondence was chiefly concerned with the election of Grigg to a Fellowship in the American Institute of Architects (1951-1953) and Grigg's acceptance into the Cosmos Club (1954). Correspondents include: Harvey Wiley Corbett, Mayor William R. Hill of Charlottesville, Frederick H. Hobbs, Jr., Fiske Kimball, Merrill C. Lee, Walter M. Macomber (1957 Mar 12), Francis Pickens Miller (1954 Jul 30), F.A. de Moleyns (1956 Oct 16), Edwin Bateman Morris, and Henry H. Saylor.
Contents List
- Photographs
  - Identified Photographs
    - Houses and Churches
      - Accomac County: n.d. (Box 1)
        Bowman's Folly (front exterior); Mt. Custis
      - Albemarle County:(Folder 1) 1941, n.d. (Box 1)
        [Everingham] Blake House, Garth Road; Burnley's Tavern, Stony Point Ordinary; [Cismont, Maury Mills ?]; Colle; Arthur Derby House, Stony Point; Farmington Houses: Cone House & Mayo House; Forest Lodge-Frank L. Parker; Glen Echo; Glenower on Totier Creek; Hollymead, Proffit; Land's End, Stony Point; Monticello
      - Albemarle County: (Folder 2) 1927, n.d. (Box 1)
        Dunlora, Rio Road; [Emmanuel Church ?], Greenwood; Estouteville; Kenwood (Watson House); Lewisfield, Free Union Road; Manahan House, Rt. 20; Mountain Grove (interior); Mountain View (door only); Round Top (previously known as Sharon); Sunnybank, North Garden
      - Albemarle County: (Folder 3) 1940-1941, n.d. (Box 1)
        Edgemont
      - Alexandria: (Folder 1) 1936-1944, n.d. (Box 1)
        Belle Haven, Residence of Richard B. English; Christ Church Parish House; First Church of Christian Science
      - Alexandria: (Folder 2) 1941, n.d. (Box 1)
        [Gadsby Tavern ?]; General; Grace Church; Anna Jones House; Bernard Knight House
      - Amelia County 1932 (Box 1)
        Hindle House
      - Bedford County: n.d. (Box 1)
        Poplar Forest (privy, fireplace); Woodburne (doors, fireplace)
      - Botetourt County: n.d. (Box 1)
        Fincastle (fireplace)
      - Buckingham County: n.d. (Box 1)
        Cello; [Courthouse stairs?]; Old Colonial Home for Tourists
      - Caroline County: 1936 (Box 1)
        Bowling Green
      - Charles City County: 1931-1937, n.d. (Box 1)
        Glebe House; Greenway; Weyanoke
      - Charlottesville: (Folder 1) 1940's, n.d. (Box 2)
        Albemarle Hotel Dining Room; James Burnley House, Fenall Avenue; Courthouse and City Hall; Eleanor Harrison House, Hessian Road; Dr. James Kindred House, Hessian Road; The National Bank; Old Christ Church; Thomas Jefferson Inn; [Wit's End ?], Mark Henderson House, Cameron Lane
      - Charlottesville: (Folder 2) ca. 1924-1950 (Box 2)
        Basham Farm Cottage, Rio Road; Branch Library; Jane Hashagen House, Hessian Road; Lee House, Spottswood Road; Evan J. Male House, Spottswood Road; Everard Meade House, Valley Road; [Everett] Meade House, Valley Road; [Michie Tavern]; O'Neill House, Cameron Lane; W. W. Parks House, Hessian Road; Ridge Street House; [Southeast Corner, 9th Street]; Street Scenes of Old Charlottesville; Thomas Towles House, Thompson Road; Via House, West Main Street
      - Charlottesville: 1947-1961 (Box 2)
        Grigg Residence on Hessian Road
      - Charlottesville: 1947-1948 (Box 2)
        Photograph Album Showing the Construction of the Grigg Residence on Hessian Road
      - Charlottesville: University of Virginia 1920s, n.d. (Box 2)
        Memorial Gym (Boxing Exhibition); Monroe Hill; Nu Chapter House, Kappa Sigma; Pavilion IX, Watercolor, Rotunda
      - Clarke County n.d. (Box 2)
        Greenway Court (postcard); Old Chapel near Millwood (postcards)
      - Cumberland County: St. James Church n.d. (Box 2)
        Floor plan
      - Essex County: 1936, n.d. (Box 2)
        Bathurst, Vawter's Episcopal Church
      - Fairfax County 1955, n.d. (Box 2)
        Courthouse; Falls Church; Ernest Randolph Follin House; Pohick Church; St. John's Church, McLean; St. Paul's Church, Baileys Crossroads
      - Fluvanna County: n.d. (Box 2)
        Bremo Smokehouse; Caldwell House, near Palmyra, House (Unidentified)
      - Fredericksburg: n.d. (Box 2)
        Kenmore; Rising Sun Tavern
      - Gloucester County: n.d. (Box 2)
        Abingdon Church; Argyle; Glebe House; Long Bridge Ordinary; [Toddsbury] (interior views)
      - Goochland County: n.d. (Box 2)
        Tuckahoe
      - Hanover: Tavern n.d. (Box 2)
      - Henrico County: Wilton n.d. (Box 2)
      - James City County: Green Spring n.d. (Box 2)
      - King and Queen County: Hillsborough 1936 (Box 2)
      - Lancaster County: 1937, n.d. (Box 2)
        Belle Isle, St. Mary's Whitechapel, Towle's Point
      - Leesburg: [Church] n.d. (Box 2)
      - Lexington: Washington & Lee University n.d. (Box 2)
      - Loudoun County: Fendall House (fireplace) 1930 (Box 2)
      - Nansemond: Chuckatuck (gateposts) 1936 (Box 3)
      - New Kent County 1936, n.d. (Box 3)
        The Castle; Criss Cross, Poindexter House (doors, exterior); St. Peter's Church
      - Northampton County: Brownsville n.d. (Box 3)
      - Orange County: n.d. (Box 3)
        Frascati Kitchen; Montpelier
      - Petersburg: Blandford Church n.d. (Box 3)
      - Prince George County, Maryland-Croome-St. Thomas Espiscopal Church n.d. (Box 3)
      - Prince William County n.d. (Box 2)
        Effingham (door detail); Merchent House
      - Princess Anne County 1934, n.d. (Box 3)
        Keeling House; Wishart House
      - Richmond: n.d. (Box 3)
        Monumental Church; Rutherford House
      - Richmond County: 1937 (Box 3)
        Indian Banks
      - Stafford County: n.d. (Box 3)
        Falmouth
      - Surrey County n.d. (Box 3)
        Bacon's Castle
      - Warrenton: n.d. (Box 3)
        Courthouse
      - Warwick County: n.d. (Box 3)
        Matthew Jones House
      - Williamsburg 1930-1932, n.d. (Box 3)
        Emmalou Barlow House; Richard Bland House; Bracken Hall; [Bourbon House], East Francis Street; Bruton Parish Churchyard; Christian House, Duke of Gloucester Street; [Courthouse ?]; Galt House; Lottie Garrett House, Nicholson Street; Governor's Palace; Grigg Residence on Francis Street; Moorecock-Waller House, Francis Street; Poplar Hall; Powder Horn
      - Williamsburg: (Cont.) 1930-1932, n.d. (Box 3)
        St. Stephens Lutheran Church, Semple House, Francis Street; [Sweet Hall ?]; Tenements; Tucker House
      - Williamsburg: n.d. (Box 3)
        Unidentified
      - Winchester n.d. (Box 3)
      - Wytheville: n.d. (Box 3)
        St. John's Episcopal Church
      - Yorktown: n.d. (Box 3)
        Cole-Digges House; Moore House; Nelson Tomb; Shield House; West House
    - Miscellaneous Photographs
      - Grigg Family ca. 1924-1972 (Box 3)
      - Houses: Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 3)
        Chalybeate Springs, [Alleghany County ?]; [Gordonsdale ?], Fauquier County; House in Worsham, Prince Edward County; [Jamestown ?] Church; Kinsole Manor; R. D. Moore House Hall Fixture (drawing); Rice's Hotel, Heathsville, Northumberland County; Sara's Creek (living room, front elevation, & stair hall); Study for Solarium Army Medical Center, Walter Reed Hospital
      - Professional Architecture Organizations Photographs 1950-1976 (Box 3)
      - Matted Photographs 1964, n.d., Oversize, 5 photographs
        taken by Grigg for the Charlottesville Camera Club
  - Unidentified Photgraphs
    - Churches 1967-1972, n.d., 3 folders (Box 4)
      Unidentified Exterior Views
    - Churches n.d. (Box 4)
      Unidentified Interior Views
    - Houses n.d., 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Houses 1971, n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Houses n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
      Unidentified Furniture & Interior Views
- Miscellaneous Files
  - Architectural Projects of Milton Grigg 1942-1972 (Box 5)
  - Bayly Museum Exhibition of Early Views of Albemarle County, Virginia 1939 (Box 5)
  - Biographical Information ca. 1940-1982 (Box 5)
    re Milton Grigg, including portrait photographs of Grigg
  - Church Architectural Guild Tour of Europe 1961 (Box 5)
  - Church Projects by Milton Grigg (B-H) 1955-1980, n.d. (Box 5)
    Braddock Street United Methodist Church, Winchester, Va; Bush Hill United Presbyterian Church; Christ Evangelical Lutheran Church, Staunton, Va.; Church of the Ascension, Virginia Beach, Va; Church of the Holy Communion, Congress Heights, Washington, D. C.; Emmanuel Church, Harrsionburg, Va.; Espiscopal Church of the Advent, Annadale, Va., Fairfax Prebyterian Church, Fairfax, Va.; Falls Church, The City of Falls Church, Va., First Church of Christ, Scientist, Roanoke, Va.; First Presbyterian Church, Greenville, N.C., First Presbyterian Church, Winston-Salem, N.C.; First Presbyterian Church of the Covenant, Arlington, Va.; First Presbyterian Church [?]; Goodson Chapel and Recital Hall of the Shenandoah; College and Conservatory of Music; Grace Church, Kilmarnock, Va.; Grace Episcopal Church, Alexandria, Va.; Grace Evangelical Lutheran Church, Waynesboro, Va.; Hidenwood Presbyerian Church, Newport News, Va.; Holy Trinity Luthern Church, Falls Church, Va.
  - Church Projects by Milton Grigg (K-Z) 1945-1976, n.d. (Box 5)
    Kirkwood Presbyterian Church; Luther Memorial Lutherian Church, Blacksburg, Va.; Lutheran Church of the Good Shepherd, Virginia Beach; Northampton Presbyterian Church Building, Hampton, Va.; Orange Presbyterian Church, Orange, Va.; St. Alban's Church and Parish House, Annadale, Va.; St. James Church, Cartersville, Va.; St. James Lutheran Church, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania; St. James the Less, Ashland, Va.; St. James United Methodist Church; St. John's Episcopal Church, McLean, Va.; St. John's Church, King William County, Va.; St. John's Lutheran Church, Emporia, Va.; St. Stephen Church, Williamsburg, Va.; St. Thomas Catholic Center, University of Virginia; St. Thomas Episcopal Church, Columbus, Georgia; St. Thomas Episcopal Church, Thomasville, Georgia; Second Presbyterian Church, Waynesboro, Va.; Temple Beth-El, Alexandria, Va.; Trinity Lutheran Church, Richmond, Va.; Virginia Methodist Home for the Aged, Chapel, Richmond; Washington Street Methodist Church, Alexandria, Va.; Zion Union Baptist Church, Charlottesville, Va.
  - Correspondence 1936-1981, n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1961-1979, n.d. (Box 5)
  - Reel-to-Reel Audiotape n.d. (Box 5)
    for use in conjunction with one of Grigg's slide show presentations concerning church architecture
  - Slide Show Presentation Notes 1955-1962, n.d., 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Trip to Australia 1958 (Box 5)
  - Blueprint of Belle Haven, Residence for Richard B. English 1934, Oversize
  - Blueprint of Edgemont, Albemarle County, Plan at Principal Storey 1937, Oversize
  - Blueprint of Manager's House for the Estate of Howard D. Froelick, Carter's Bridge, Albemarle County 1936, Oversize
  - Photostats of the Virginia World War II Memorial n.d., Oversize, 8 sheets